About

I'm a Software Development Engineer interested in large scale systems and the Web. I have 3.5 years of experience in software engineering and have been programming for over 12 years. My primary development experience is in back-end programming in Java, C#, JavaScript, and Python; writing agent/batch/job-oriented systems for financial systems, system administration for Windows and UNIX, hardware/computer engineering and robust control software. A lot of the software I have designed and implemented is publicly available on <u>GitHub</u>.

Other Résumé versions: PDF, One-page PDF, MS Word, One-page MS Word, JSON Résumé

Education

 Master of Information Engineering in Computer Science, 2015, Autonomous University of Nuevo León. Overall Grade 94.5/100.0

Courses:

- O Research Methodology
- Quantitative Methods (Statistics)
- O Discrete Mathematics for Geometric Design
- O Programming and Simulation
- **O** Information Systems
- O Object Oriented Programming
- O Database Management and Design
- O E-Business Oriented Information Systems
- o Computer Science Seminar
- O Management of Information Technology Projects
- O Technologies for Internet Information Security
- Technologies for Organizational Change
- O Information Technology Management and Planning
- O Decision Support Systems
- O Human-computer Interaction
- Bachelor in Mechatronics Engineering, 2012, Autonomous University of Nuevo León.
 Graduated with honors (Mención Honorífica de Excelencia), Overall Grade 95.9/100.0

Courses:

- O Basic Programming
- O Probability and Statistics
- o Discrete Mathematics
- o Data Structures
- Advanced Programming
- o Theoretical Computer Science
- O Digital Electronics
- Object Oriented Programming
- O Data Acquisition
- o Robot Architecture
- O Artificial Intelligence and Neural Networks
- O Project Management
- O Human-Computer Interaction
- o Machine Vision
- 0 Perception
- O Machine Perception

Experience

Self-employment/Freelancing, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico

Instructor. 2015-2016. Coached job applicants and students on computer science and software engineering topics.

- Designed custom study plans based on assessment of the client's knowledge and skills via tests and interviews
- Did one-on-one mock interviews and provided feedback afterward
- Published implementations of data structures, algorithms, and solutions to programming problems.
 See <u>Data structures and algorithms in C#</u>, <u>Software engineering problems in JavaScript</u>, <u>Software engineering problems in C#</u>, <u>pysweng: Software engineering problems in Python</u> and <u>Data structures</u> and algorithms in JavaScript
- Environment: Java, C#, Python, JavaScript, Node.js, .NET Core, Visual Studio Code, xUnit, JUnit, Mocha, Maven

Self-employment/Freelancing, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico

Technical Writer. 2015-2016. Wrote technical documentation on topics such as programming, system administration, audio/video processing and production, and security.

- Published more than 45 technical notes at http://pedroivanlopez.com/tech-notes
- Some of the software tools and applications I wrote about are Fedora Linux, FFmpeg, Windows, Python, JavaScript, Node.js, OpenSSH, Git, Android, Anki, Cygwin, Audacity, among others
- Environment: Jekyll, Markdown, Fedora, Windows, Python

Infosys Ltd, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico

Systems Engineer, January 2013 to February 2015. Contractor for a Fortune 100 multinational banking and financial services corporation. Development, administration and support team for a global trade finance application used mainly in North America and Asia

- Coded and tested new agents/batch-jobs and features in Java, C#, JavaScript and Windows Batch
- Designed and implemented a Windows Script Host script in JavaScript to retrieve scanned image and metadata files from the scanner workstations to our server and prepare for further processing
- Fixed 350 incidents, including code bugs, development of new features, customers with invalid data in production and outages
- On-call primary contact for 20 weeks
- Led 30 Request For Change procedures to install code updates and to update data via SQL scripts
- Supported production and test environments for clients and other teams in the bank
- Knowledge management via documentation of known issues and fixes, to coach offshore resources
- Environment: Java, .NET, C#, JavaScript, SQL, Bash, Hibernate, Spring, Eclipse, Toad, ClearCase, RedHat Linux, Windows Server, Autosys, Windows Script Host

Center for the Development of the Software Industry, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico. **Software Engineer**, October 2012 to January 2013. Tested and validated a financial web application and platform

- Performed testing and quality assurance of an enterprise financial Web platform for a Mexican bank, implemented in Java Enterprise Edition and JavaScript
- Types of tests performed: black box, system, functional, acceptance
- Environment: Internet Explorer, Mozilla Firefox, Excel, JavaScript

School of Physics and Mathematics at UANL, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico Research Assistant (internship), August 2011 to February 2012. Research topics: control engineering, robust control, linear systems, filters.

- Developed and maintained robust control systems software in Python, MATLAB and Simulink
- Co-authored one published paper: Basin, M.; Serna, M.; Lopez-Hernandez, P.I., <u>Central energy-to-peak filter design for uncertain linear systems</u>, Control Conference (ASCC), June 2013
- Performed system administration of workstations and maintenance of hardware units
- Environment: Python, MATLAB, LabVIEW, NI Elvis, LaTeX

School of Mechanical and Electrical Engineering at UANL, Monterrey, Nuevo León, Mexico Laboratory Assistant (internship), February 2012 to August 2012

- Supported students in designing and troubleshooting programs in Python, MATLAB and LabVIEW
- Performed system administration of workstations and maintenance of hardware units
- Assisted professors with teaching electronics and programming during laboratory sessions
- Environment: Python, MATLAB, LabVIEW, NI Elvis, LaTeX, BASIC

Computer Skills

- Languages: Python, JavaScript, C#, Java, SQL, HTML, CSS, Bash/UNIX Shell Scripting, VB.NET,
 MATLAB, LabVIEW, XSLT, LaTeX
- Data/Databases: Microsoft SQL Server, Oracle, MySQL, SQLite, JSON, YAML, XML
- **Technologies**: .NET, Java, Node.js, xUnit, ASP.NET 4 & 5, ASP.NET MVC 5, Docker, Spring, Hibernate, ASP.NET Web Forms, Java EE, Jekyll, Sphinx documentation tools, leJOS
- Design patterns: Dependency Injection, Object-Relational Mapping (ORM), Module, Factory method, Iterator, Reactor, Singleton, Observer
- Architectural patterns: Inversion of Control, Event-driven architecture, Model-View-Controller
- Applications: Microsoft Visual Studio, Visual Studio Code, Git, ClearCase, Toad, Eclipse, Cygwin, Vim, GNU Make, Ant, IPython, OpenSSH, Maven
- Operating Systems: UNIX (Fedora, Ubuntu, Red Hat Enterprise Linux, Android), Microsoft Windows (Server 2003, XP, Vista, 7, 8, 10)
- Other: Linux user for 8 years, proficient with UNIX command line interface, technical documentation writing, homebuilt computers enthusiast

Languages

- English: Full professional proficiency
- **Spanish**: Native speaker

Projects

- **ASPNET5CO**: Advocacy and Community. Efforts to advocate the ASP.NET Core framework, http://pedroivanlopez.com/aspnet5co
- Data structures and algorithms in C#:
 https://github.com/lopezpdvn/DataStructuresAlgorithmsCSharp
- mazerob: Bluetooth-remote-control robot implemented with Java Virtual Machines on a PC and a Lego NXT Brick, http://pedroivanlopez.com/mazerob
- printer73x: A computer numerical control system for printing binary images, http://pedroivanlopez.com/printer73x
- **cerca**: A distance measurement system running on a personal computer and an 8-bit microcontroller http://pedroivanlopez.com/cerca
- pysyspol: Cross-platform system policy for applications and environments with Python https://github.com/lopezpdvn/pysyspol
- syspol-js: Cross-platform system policy for applications and environments with JavaScript https://github.com/lopezpdvn/syspol-js

- dotfiles: Miscellaneous configuration files and directories https://github.com/lopezpdvn/dotfiles
- Software engineering problems in C#:
 https://github.com/lopezpdvn/SoftwareEngineeringProblemsCSharp
- resources-viewer: Browser based static app for viewing resources https://github.com/lopezpdvn/resources-viewer
- timeman: Simple time management types, https://github.com/lopezpdvn/timeman
- **syspol**: Cross-platform system policy for applications and environments https://github.com/lopezpdvn/syspol
- **swebserv**: Java program that simulates Denial-of-service attacks on HTTP/web servers https://github.com/lopezpdvn/swebserv

For other projects see my <u>technical notes</u>, as well as my <u>Github</u> and <u>Gist</u> profiles.

Publications

Control Conference (ASCC). 23 June 2013. http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?
 tp=&arnumber=6606296&isnumber=6605987

This paper presents the central finite-dimensional energy-to-peak filter for linear systems that is optimal with respect to a modified Bolza-Meyer quadratic criterion including the first degree state-dependent term and the attenuation control term with the opposite sign. The obtained solution is based on reducing the original energy-to-peak filtering problem to the corresponding mean-module filtering problem, using the technique proposed in [1].

Technical notes. Self-published, http://pedroivanlopez.com/tech-notes/
 Technical documentation on topics such as programming, system administration, audio/video processing and production, and security.